Europass Curriculum Vitae



Personal information

First name(s) / Surname(s)

Emanuele Braga

Address(es)

Via Villapizzone 26 20156 Milano (Italy)

Telephone(s)

+39 3407139053

Fax(es)

E-mail

bragaberlino@gmail.com

Nationality

italian

Date of birth

27/12/75

Gender

Disidentificated

Desired employment / Occupational field

Researcher, Artist, Activist

Co-founder of Balletto Civile dance company in which he operated as a choreographer, performer and teacher.

Active in various contexts on the issues of the relationship between art, economy, labour and new technologies.

Founder of the contemporary art collective Rhaze in which he operated as artist Co-Founder and developer of Macao, new centre for art and culture in Milano.

Co- Founder of Landscape Choreography cross-sectors, performative and research project, in which he operated as director and researcher.

Co-founder of Coop of the Commons.

Co-founder of IRI Institute of Radical Imagination

Professor of Big Data and Digital Methods in the Milano State University.

Work experience

Dates 2018-2019

Occupation or position held professor

Main activities and responsibilities teacher

Name and address of employer Big Data and Digital Methods at the MA of the Social Science Department,

Sate University of Milano (IT)

Type of business or sector academic

Dates 2018-2019

Occupation or position held president

Main activities and responsibilities co-founder

Name and address of employer | Coop of the commons S.C.E, Milano (IT)

Type of business or sector Alternative Economy and New Technology

Page 1/8 - Curriculum vitae of Surname(s) First name(s)

For more information on Europass go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu © European Union, 2004-2010 24082010

Dates 2011-2019

Occupation or position held Art Director and Curator

Main activities and responsibilities Artistic Director of the project LANDSCAPE CHOREOGRAPHY

Name and address of employer Landscape choreography is based in Milano (IT) and did site specific projects at Santarcangelo Festival

(IT), Mantova city council, Berlin city council (DE), Ebony Decolonize work (MI), Mare Culturale Urbano (MI), Miami University (US), Leibniz Universität Hannover, urban landscape design, Hannover, (DE), Universität von Siena (Università degli studi di Siena), Anthropologies, Siena, (IT), studio LOV, landscape

+ architecture, Berlin, (DE), LABuat, urban and architectural research Laboratory, Taranto, (IT), Hochschule Lausitz, INIK, Institute Of New Industrial Culture, Cottbus, (DE), Collectiv A, cultural

Association, Cluj-Napoca, (RO)

Type of business or sector Art, Urbanism, Design. Game design, Dance, Architecture, and theorical research in landscape-

anthropology-choreography.

Dates 2013-2017

Occupation or position held | Artistic Director and Curator

Main activities and responsibilities | Curator and Artistic Director of the project CITY ON THE MOVE

author of F***ing Good Talent (show) and IL FUTURO ERA ORA (art/design/social research) R as

REPUBLIC (art/design/social research) and the book MAUZ7 (urban and social analysis)

Name and address of employer | Mare culturale urbano, Milano (IT)

Type of business or sector | Art

Dates 2015

Occupation or position held Researcher and coordinator

Main activities and responsibilities "IS THIS WORKING?" Sociological research on future scenarios of labour

work field EXPO2015 Word exposition. Title of the research: Is This Working?

Name and address of employer Robin Hood Minor Asset Management (FL) and Macao (IT)

Type of business or sector | Work sociology, Post-capitalism, Alternative economy and new Technology, performance

Dates 2015 - 2016

Occupation or position held Researcher and choreographer - director

Main activities and responsibilities | Let's walk in the urban landscape

Name and address of employer |Libniz University of Hannover (DE) and University of MIAMI (US)

Type of business or sector | Landscape, performing art, urbanism

Dates 2014

Occupation or position held Researcher and choreographer - director

Main activities and responsibilities | Asfalto Mon Amour (urban design, and show)

Name and address of employer | Manifatture Knoss

Type of business or sector | Landscape, performing art, urbanism

Dates 2011

Occupation or position held | Visual artist

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author and Choreography of the public art project 'The show everybody wants', Biennale di

Venezia.

Name and address of employer | Freelancer, Rha ze, the danish pavilion, Isola di san Servolo Venezia italy, 54 Biennale di Venezia,

ARTRA Gallery di Milano.

Type of business or sector | Contemporary art production

Dates | 2010-2011

Occupation or position held | Theatre director

Page 2/8 - Curriculum vitae of For more information on Europass go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu

Surname(s) First name(s) © European Union, 2004-2010 24082010

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author and Choreographer of the performing art project 'L'ALA', Playing Identities, Migration

Creolisation

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Centre européen de Conques (FR), Rumanian National Theatre (RO), Museo Santa

Maria della Scala di Siena (IT)

Type of business or sector | Dance production and socio-anthropological research

Dates 2010

Occupation or position held | Choreographer and visual artist

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'Incompiuto Siciliano'

Name and address of employer | Alterazioni Video, COLOCO and Balletto Civile, Centro polifuzionale – Piscina olimpionica incompiuta,

Giarre (CT) Italy

Type of business or sector | Dance production, public art, urban planing

Dates | 2009-2010

Occupation or position held performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'Detriti'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Festival Castrovillari (CS) italy, Teatro Fondamenta Nuove di Venezia, Teatro

Ringhiera di Milano, Teatro Due di Parma, Teatro delle Passioni ERT di Modena

Type of business or sector | Dance production

Dates 2008-2009

Occupation or position held Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | performer of the performing art project 'Macbeth'

Name and address of employer | Teatro Stabile di Torino and Compangia Dioniso, Teatro Carignano di Torino(IT),

Type of business or sector | Theatre production

Dates | 2007-2008

Occupation or position held | Performer

Main activities and responsibilities performer of the performing art project "Disco pigs"

Name and address of employer Teatro Stabile di Torino and Compangia Dioniso, Teatro Cavallerizza di Torino (IT), Festival dei due

Mondi di Spoleto (IT), Teatro Due di Parma (IT), Volksbuhne in Berlin (DE)

Type of business or sector | Dance production and socio-anthropological research

Dates | 2008-2010

Occupation or position held Performer and visual artist

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'I Prodotti'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile and Artificio23, Teatro Cavallerizza di Torino (IT), Festival dei due Mondi di Spoleto (IT),

Teatro Franco Parenti di Milano (IT), Teatro Due di Parma (IT)

Type of business or sector | Dance production and socio-anthropological research

Dates 2008

Occupation or position held performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'Creatura'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Biennale di Venezia, Festival Teatro Due di Parma, Teatro Alfieri di Asti (IT)

Type of business or sector | Dance production

Dates | 2007-2009

Occupation or position held | Performer and Playwriter

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'Battesimi'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Teatro Eliseo in Rome, Theatre Out Off in Milano, Festival Andersen di Genova (IT),

Teatro Kismet di Bari (IT)

Type of business or sector | Dance production

Page 3/8 - Curriculum vitae of Surname(s) First name(s) For mo

For more information on Europass go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu © European Union, 2004-2010 24082010

Dates 2008-2009
Occupation or position held Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'Horror Vacui'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile Artificio23 and Cahin Caha, Festival Andersen (IT)

Type of business or sector | Performing art in site specific production

Dates | 2006-2007

Occupation or position held | Performer and Playwriter

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'I SETTE A TEBE'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Festival Noorderzon di Groningen (NL), Festival di Castiglioncello (IT), Experimental

Theatre Festival Cairo Opera House (EG) Css Teatro di Udine, Festival Vie di Modena (IT)

Type of business or sector | Dance production

Dates | 2004-2007

Occupation or position held Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'I TOPI'

Name and address of employer | Balletto Civile, Cairo International Book Fair (EG), Css Teatro (IT) Mittelfest di Cividale (IT) SEAS

project Intercult di Copenhagen (IT, HR, PL, RU, DK)

Type of business or sector | Dance production and cooperation program

Dates | 2002-2003

Occupation or position held Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'IL QUARTIERE'

Name and address of employer | Impasto comunità teatrale nomade, Teatro di Sant'osvaldo di Udine (IT), Teatro delle Albe di Ravenna

(IT), Teatro Carignano di Torino(IT), Festival Orestiadi di Gibellina (IT), Biennale Giovani di Torino (IT)

Type of business or sector | theatre production

Dates | 1999-2001

Occupation or position held | Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Co-Author of the performing art project 'L'AGENDA DI SEATTLE'

Name and address of employer | Impasto comunità teatrale nomade, FESTIVAL ORIENTE OCCIDENTE(IT), Teatro comunale di

Ferrara (IT), CRT Teatro dell'Arte di Milano

Type of business or sector | Dance and theatre production and sociological research

Dates | 1998-1999

Occupation or position held Performer

Main activities and responsibilities | Performer in the performing art project 'Di terra e di aria'

Name and address of employer | Quelli di Grock, Teatro Leonardo di milano, Teatro Alfieri di Pavia, Teatro delle Erbe di Mllano

Type of business or sector | theatre production

Dates 1999-2003

Occupation or position held | Editorial collaborator and translator

Main activities and responsibilities Advisor

Name and address of employer

Type of business or sector

Type of business or sector

ENGLISH NARRATIVE BOOKS

Dates

Occupation or position held | Editorial collaborator and translator

2000-2001

Main activities and responsibilities | advisor

Name and address of employer Publishing House MONDADORI, Milano

Type of business or sector | ENGLISH NARRATIVE BOOKS

Page 4/8 - Curriculum vitae of Surname(s) First name(s)

For more information on Europass go to http://europass.cedefop.europa.eu © European Union, 2004-2010 24082010

Education and training

Dates

1993-1999

Semiotics

Title of qualification awarded

Dr. Philosophy

Principal subjects/occupational skills

covered

Name and type of organisation providing education and training

Univeristà Cattolica del Sacro Cuore di Milano – Faculty of Letters and Philosophy

Level in national or international classification

Degree in Philosophy (106/110)

Personal skills and competences

Mother tongue(s)

italian

Other language(s)

Self-assessment

European level (*)

English german

Understanding				Speaking				Writing	
Listening			Reading		Spoken interaction		Spoken production		
C2	Independent user	C2	Independent user	C2	Independent user	C2	Independent user	C2	Independent user
a2	Basic User		Basic User	a2	Basic User	a2	Basic User	a2	Basic User

(*) Common European Framework of Reference for Languages

Social skills and competences

Resercher in new technologies, digital platforms and alternative economy.

Organization of cultural project, working with volunteers, in the field of mental disease, migrants and workers rights.

Organisational skills and competences

Administrator of the Associazione Culutrale Balletto Civile, Landscape Chorepgraphy, and Coop of the commons, manging the company, organizing public debates, assisting no-profit organization. Researcher in experimental schems of alternative organizations models.

Technical skills and competences

Researcher in political economy, digital paltforms, Choreographer, Visual artist, Playwriter, Theacher of theatre and Dance, Art Theory and Professor in Big Data and digital methods.

Computer skills and competences

Competent with blockchain, cryptocurrencies, software design, Microsoft Office, web editors and HTML, adobe CS5 and image editors, Final Cut and Video editing, Stop Motion, Ableton Live and audio editing, blog admin and social networks

Driving licence

yes

Additional information | PARTECIPATIONS TO ISTITUTIONAL PROGRAMS: SYMPOSIUM / KEYNOTES / TALKS

- 2009 with Balletto Civile participates in the Venice Biennale Dance.
- 2010 with Balletto Civile he takes part in the European project Playing Identities: Migration, Creolization, Creation (fr / it / ro / pl) **EU Culture Program** 2007-2013
- 2011 2013 directs the European project Landscape Choreography from wasted lands to shared spaces (en / ro / de) EU Culture Program 2007-2013
- 2013 co-curator of the symposium FARE PUBBLICI at MACAO (IT)
- 2014 co-curator of the symposium ABSTRACT STRIKE at Sale Docks in Venice and Macao (IT)
- 2016 co-curator of the symposium **PLATFORM OF THE CAPITAL** at Macao (IT)
- 2016 participates in the public program of the Athens Biennale
- 2015 collaborator of the European Project **D-CENT Technologies for 21st Century democracy**
- 2017 participates in the public program of **DOCUMENTA14** and invited by Documenta14 for a focus research on alternative economy for contemporary art in a sires of meeting titled "The Conclave", that continued in the project of Parliament of the Bodies: the Cooperative Society.
- 2016 participates in **MoneyLab#4** of Institute of Network Culture in Amsterdam, presenting a report on "Blockchain and governance, the future of algorithms".
- 2017 participate in Swap What about politics? by IMAL, center for digital culture and techno- logies presenting "Commoncoin and Bank of the Commons".
- 2018 collaborator of the european project **Commonfare**.
- 2017 2019 with Macao he participates for three years at the Santarcangelo Festival developing an open data project, and developing alternative digital monetary circuits in cultural production for the construction of community welfare, in collaboration with the European project Commonfare.
- 2018 participates at Contempray Art FORUM at Mambo in Bologna
- 2018 co-founder of the IRI Insitute of Radial Imagination. https://instituteofradicalimagination.org/
- 2018 participates in Asilo MACRO in Rome
- 2019 participates in SISEC Società Italiana di Socilogia Economica, Sviluppo e disuquaglianze a Nord del Sud e a Sud del nord del mondo
- 2019 keynote in VOLKSBÜHNE School of Disobedience:\Experimentations in Alternative Economies.
- 2019 participates in MoneyLab#6 of Institute of Network Culture in Siegen
- 2019 participates in **Blokchain Parade** of Gaité Lyrique in Paris

ACADEMIC TEACHINGS

He taught with Balletto Civile at the **Teatro Stabile in Turin**, and at the specialization school of the European actor at the **Teatro Stabile of Parma**

He collaborates with the Master of Visual Arts and Design, Dirty art department at the **Sandberg Institute ofAmsterdam** (NL), with whom he is responsible for the special Wandering School project.

He has collaborated with the course of Architecture and Design of the **Miami University** in Cincinnati (US)

He has collaborated to the master of Architecture and urban planning of the university **BTU** of Cottbus (DE)

He has held workshops of economic politics and alternative currencies to the **Bocconi University** of Milan

He has held design and urban planning workshop at the **Domus Academy** in Milan He held urban planning and performing arts workshops at the **Leibniz Universität** in Hannover. He has worked with **Goldsmith University** (UK)

He is actually teaching Big Data at the MA of the Social Sience Department, **Sate University of Milano** (IT)

PUBLICATIONS

With Andrea Fumagalli, he curated the edition of La Moneta del Comune, the challenge of the financial institution of the Commons, Derive Approdi 2014

Contributes to Currency_04, Spacegoat Architecture Landscape Political Economy, 2013

Cure for Landscape Choreography and Cohabitation Strategies, the book for children, **Abecedario dei gesti del futuro**, Mare Culturale Urbano edizioni, 2015

Contributes to **Making Cultural Production in Occupied Spaces**, curated by Alan Moore and Alan Smart, Other Forms and Journal of Aesthetics and Protest 2016

Contributes to **artWORK**, **art labor and activism** by Alberto Cossu, Jessica Holtaway and Paula Serfini, Rowan & Littlefield International 2017

Contributes to **The Revolt of Cooperation**, social experimentation and possible autonomy, curated by Andrea Fumagalli, Giovanni Giovannelli and Cristina Morini, Meltemi Edizioni 2018

PAPERS AND ARTICLES:

INFRASTRUCTURES FOR FUTURE ECOSYSTEMS Scenarios and visions based on experimentations in alternative economies: the case of CommonCoin, FairCoin, and Bank of the Commons

http://networkcultures.org/moneylab/2019/02/25/infrastructures-for-future-ecosystems/

IL FUTURO E IL SUO DOPPIO

http://effimera.org/il-futuro-e-il-suo-doppio-di-emanuele-braga/

CONTEMPORARY ART IS OUT OF JOINT! Macao: produzione simbolica e sistema dell'arte https://operavivamagazine.org/contemporary-art-is-out-of-joint/

IS THIS WORKING? THE FUTURE OF WORK IN EXPO

http://www.macaomilano.org/spip.php?article74

LA POLITICA DELL'ALGORITMO

http://www.macaomilano.org/spip.php?article64

Degree in Theatre Academy 'Quelli di Grock' Milano in 1995-1998

and he studied Dance and theatre with:

Pippo del Bono 1997

Michele Abbondanza 2001

Michela Lucenti 1999-2002

Erica Giovannini 1996-1998

Utlima vez Wim Vandekeybus Company 2007

Contemporary art Residencies and Exibitions:

Pensare L'arte, Fondazione Querini Stampalia di Venezia, Jean Baudrillard, Josef Kossuth and Paolo Fabbri 1999

Aesthetic Communities and Contextual Translation of Communal Art, 5th Summer Seminars for Art Curators 2010, Aica Yerevan Armenia

Stateless Pavillion 54 Biennale di Venezia

Milano Radicale, Radical Intention art residency, Corniolo Firenze 2011

Frassineto Po Parcoi 2012

Artra gallery, Milano (IT)

Rotor gallery, Graz (AT)

Macao art centre, Milano (IT)

Mare culturale urbano, Milano (IT)

Dirty Art Department, Sandberg Institute, Amsterdam(NL)

documenta 14 (DE, GR)

Festival di Santarcangelo (IT)